PROFESSOR: So let's talk
about probabilities.
This whole Expectimax thing isn't
going to work unless we've got
probabilities in there that we know
what to do with, we know what they
are, they represent the right thing.
And that's going to be a theme going
forward in this course--
that we're going to need to be able to
assign probabilities to various things
and do computations with them.
Let's remember what probabilities are.
So here's some key concepts.
We have this notion of
a random variable.
A random variable is our way
of representing an event
whose outcome is unknown.
However, while the outcome is unknown,
we have a probability distribution,
which is an assignment of weights
to the various outcomes.
See the example shown
here on the right?
This is a model of traffic where traffic
can take on three different
values, none light or heavy.
Notice this is already a model.
You might disagree.
You might want this to be
a continuous value.
Density of cars, something like that.
I've made a modeling choice.
There are three outcomes here.
Given these three outcomes, I've picked
one particular probability
distribution.
This probability distribution says, half
the time there is light traffic,
a quarter of the time there is no
traffic, and a quarter of the time
there is heavy traffic.
There are different possible choices
for this distribution.
For example, if this road is
the 880 with probability 1,
there's heavy track.
Now, these numbers that we assign
have to obey certain laws.
We're going to get to more of this
later, but for now, all we really need
is that the probabilities have to be
non-negative, and they have to add up
to 1 over all of the options.
And these probabilities
shown here obey that.
Now in general--
and we'll spend a lot of this
course unpacking this idea--
we'll be computing these
probabilities.
And as we get more evidence, the
probabilities will change.
So for example, it may be that all else
equal, the probability of heavy
traffic might be 20%, but the
probability of heavy traffic at 8 AM
may be 60%.
And this process of, given information
that we know, computing the
appropriate probabilities, is
probabilistic inference, and we will
spend a great deal of time on
that later in this course.
The one other thing that we need for
Expectimax is the expecti- part.
That's expectations.
And the expected value of a function
of a random variable is just an
average, and it's a weighted average
where the outcomes, function values,
are all weighted by whatever the
probability distribution says.
So for example, if we wanted to know how
long it would take to get to the
airport, that's going to be
a function of the traffic.
And so what I would do is I'd say,
all right, it's going to
depend on the traffic.
And here the three values
and their probabilities.
For each of those values, there's some
associated function value-- in this
case, the time.
And then to compute the expectation, I
just multiply each probability times
function value, add them up, and I
end up with my expected value.
That's exactly what we've been
doing at these chance nodes.
They're simply expectations
of the children's values--
Expectimax values--
weighted by the probabilities.
OK.
So great.
What probabilities should we use?
Well, in an Expectimax search, these
chance nodes reflect what we think the
relative chances are of
the various outcomes.
Sometimes that's easy.
For example, sometimes I'm going to roll
a die, and I know that each of
the six outcomes on a six-sided die
are equally likely, and then I can
just use even weights.
But sometimes it can be
very sophisticated.
For example, if I'm trying to figure
out what a ghost is doing, I might
observe the ghost, I might take some
notes, I might take the temperature of
the air, and then I might do some
computation and say, under these
circumstances, I think the chance that
the ghost will go left is 30%.
We'll get to how to do that later,
but for now, realize that these
probabilities can require a
lot of work to compute.
Every single outcome that's out of our
control, whether it's an opponent our
an environment, has a chance node
in the Expectimax tree.
The probabilities reflect our belief
as to what will happen.
There's nothing to say that our
belief, and therefore those
probabilities, shouldn't put a lot of
probability on the adversarial action.
And we'll talk about this relationship
a little later.
One important thing to remember
is that just because we assign
probabilities that reflect our beliefs
as to the outcome does not mean that
the thing on the other side
is flipping coins.
If I think there is a 20% chance that
the ghost is going to go to the left,
it doesn't mean that the ghost has
a random number generator.
It just means that given my model, which
may be a simplification, that's
the best I can say, given my evidence.
So where do the probabilities
come from?
Well, for today, they come from
the probability fairy.
We think for today that the definition
of the problem includes the
probabilities.
Later in the course, we'll have to
figure out ways to really compute them
in a given context.